Mss.947.L64
American Philosophical Society
Journal of a voyage from the Thames to Russia and of campaigning with the Russian army, 1738-1739
Mss.947.L64
American Philosophical Society
2.0 Volume(s) 2 volumes, 438 p.
Volume one includes an account of a voyage from England to St. Petersburg and of a journey from thence by Moscow through Poland to meet the Russian army. Plates consist chiefly of plans of battle fields. Volume one contains also List of expenses in the German language. A short index to various articles that are not in the volume. Project de commerce entre l'Angleterre et la Russie. Oraison funebre prononcé a St. Petersbourg le 10 Mars, 1725 a l'occasion de la lort de Pierre le Grand...par M. Theoplane... Volume two includes a section entitled "Literæ processus ssmi domini nostri Clementis--Papæ XII."
Crawford, John Lindsay,Earl of,1702-1749.
Volume 1-2
Related Archival Materials note
Lindsay's papers are continued in other manuscript volumes held by the APS: Account of some campaigns of the British army from 1689 to 1712 and a journal of a campaign under Prince Eugene on the Upper Rhine, 1689-1735 (Mss. 940 M68); Journal of a campaign with the Russian army against Turkey, 1737-1739 (Mss. 947 J82).
Scope and Contents note
The maps in the volume were drawn by Henry Kopp, secretary and draughtsman for Lord Crawford. They are inscribed to George II, king of England; Lord Loudoun, etc.
The actual dates on which the maps were drawn is conjectural. These volumes were most probably prepared for Earl Crawford between 1743 and 1747 so they could be better seen and studied in the family's muniment room.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Much of this set, along with the other manuscript volumes of Lindsay's papers, were reproduced by Richard Rolt, Memoirs of the life of the Right. Hon. John Lindsay, Earl of Crawford and Lindsay (London: 1753).
Early American History Note
This is one of four large volumes that were part of Benjamin Franklin's personal library. The four volumes comprise a series of John Lindsay Crawford’s travels with the Russian Army from 1737-1739. The volumes have large maps of Europe.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Library of Benjamin Franklin. See in-house shelf list for additional accession number.
Custodial History note
Purchased from the library of Benjamin Franklin, 1803.
Biographical/Historical note
John Lindsay, earl of Crawford and Lindsay (1702-1749), was a soldier. A Scotsman, he fought all over Europe. He was a captain in the British army and was permitted to join the Imperial army under Prince Eugene. In 1738 he received the rank of general from the Czarina Anna and fought against the Turks. He returned to the imperial forces and continued to fight until the Peace of London of 1748.
Beyond Early America; England -- Description and travel -- Early works to 1800.; Journals (notebooks).; Manuscript Essays; Maps.; Military History; Military maneuvers.; Military Records; Russia -- History, Military -- To 1801.; Travel Narratives and Journals; Voyages and travels.
- Maps
  - Theatre of war between Russian Imperial army and the Turks and Tartars, 1736 and 1737 (Crimea), 1743-1747; 1 map, 191.8 x 47.6 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Colored, on printed map.
    Other Finding Aids note
    Realms of Gold, 29 (40).
  - Ordre de bataille de l'Armée Principate de sa Majesté Impériale de toutes les Russies, 1743-1747; 1 map, 67.3 x 45.1 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 1)
    Colored.
    Realms of Gold, 29 (41).
  - Plan of the operations of the Russian Army upon the banks of the Dneister, 1738, 1 map, 143.5 x 50.8 cm, with 8.9 cm.-high title piece; Kopp, Henry (Volume 1)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (42).
  - Town of Essek (?), 1743-1747; 1 map, 72.4 x 52.1 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 1)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (43).
  - Plan von Peterwardein, 1743-1747; 1 map, 105.4 x 63.5 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 1)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (44).
  - Order of battle of His Imperiale Majestys Army in Hungary commanded by...Konigseck, 1743-1747; 1 map, 173.4 x 46.4 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (45).
  - Belgrade, 1743-1747; 1 map, 52 x 35.6 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (46).
  - Demolition de Panzowa (Pancevo), 1743-1747; 1 map, 24.8 x 43.8 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (47).
  - Plan van Temesewar, 1743-1747; 1 map, 69.2 x 56.5 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (48).
  - Plan und project von Temesewar, 1743-1747; 1 map, 69.2 x 56.5 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (49).
  - Plan von Banjalucka, 1743-1747; 1 map, 74.3 x 22.9 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (50).
  - Plan von der Haupt Festung Commoren, 1743-1747; 1 map, 94.6 x 64.1 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (51).
  - Plan der Festung Ratsche, 1743-1747; 1 map, 38 x 26 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (52).
  - Plan der Kay Vestung und Insul Orsova, 1743-1747; 1 map, 216.5 x 66.7 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (53).
  - Plan de redoute der Insul Orsova gegenuber, 1743-1747; 1 map, 64.8 x 47 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (54).
  - Vestung Bender, 1743-1747; 1 map, 58.4 x 45.7 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (55).
  - Plan de la vielle et nouvelle fortification de la ville d'Oczakov, 1743-1747; 1 map, 71.8 x 49.5 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (56).
  - Project pour fortifier la ville de Belgrade, 1743-1747; 1 map, 89.5 x 62.9 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (57).
  - Projet de Monsieur le General de Wutquinaw pour fortifier Belgrade, 1743-1747; 1 map, 45.1 x 29.8 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (58).
  - Profil von Belgrade, 1743-1747; 1 map, 72.4 x 50.2 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (59).
  - Plan of the battle of Krotska in the year 1739, 1743-1747; 1 map, 89.5 x 57.8 cm; Kopp, Henry (Volume 2)
    Realms of Gold, 29 (60).